The idea that covered calls generate
income is financial These
strategies are mechanically expected to
underperform their underlying equity and
increasingly so at higher targeted
levels of distributions. For long-term
investors, covered calls increase risk
by leaving the downside unprotected
while capping the upside, eliminating
the mean reverting behavior of stocks,
an important feature of stock returns.
I'm Ben Felix, chief investment officer
at PWL Capital, and I'm going to tell
you why the so-called passive income
from covered calls is a devil's bargain.
The preference for income is one of the
strongest behavioral biases in
investing. It can make people do silly
things in their search for income. Some
investors look for funds that pay high
distributions. This is well known by
fund managers who use high distribution
yields to attract investor dollars. The
problem for investors is that marketing
these yields in the case of covered
calls as income or even worse as
expected returns is financial
is not a lie to be clear. It is
indifference for the truth. Selling a
high distribution yield as an expected
return ignores the fact that yields on
covered call strategies are inversely
related to their expected returns.
Higher yields mechanically mean lower
expected total returns. Total returns,
to be clear, are what you need to buy
groceries. I'm going to walk through why
distribution yields are not returns, how
covered calls reduce expected returns,
and why I think the return profile of
covered calls makes them particularly
risky for long-term investors. To avoid
being too theoretical, I'm also going to
go through the performance of a bunch of
covered call funds to show that what I'm
saying is not just theoretical. It is
exactly what's happening in the live
funds. Let's start with some background.
Selling a call option on an equity that
you own generates income and creates a
liability that empirically more than
offsets the income received. This makes
the distribution yield uncovered call
funds a misleading metric. Selling a
call option means selling the right to
buy the underlying stock at a
predetermined price called the strike
price in exchange for a premium. An
equity covered call strategy invests in
stocks and sells call options on those
stocks. A fund using the strategy
typically distributes the derivative
income from selling calls as cash to
investors, resulting in their high
distribution yields. While those
distributions may feel like investment
returns, selling the call is only the
first step in the trade. The fund has
sold the right to buy the underlying
stock at the strike price. If the price
of the underlying rises above the strike
price, the option holder, who the fund
sold the option to, will exercise their
call option, and the fund will have to
sell the stock at a price below its
market value, putting a cap on upside
returns. Okay, I want to dig a little
deeper into the mechanics of what's
going on from the perspective of
expected returns. Call options are
positively exposed to their underlying
equity measured by a term called delta.
Buying a call option on a stock gives
you positive exposure to the price
movements of that stock. Selling a call
on an asset that you own, a covered
call, reduces your exposure to the
underlying stock. You're shorting
exposure to the underlying equity by
selling the call option. Holding option
maturity constant, call option prices
and deltas monotonically increase in a
decreasing strike price. If you want
higher income on your covered call
strategy, you can sell options with
lower strike prices resulting in higher
income and importantly higher short
delta. This is crucial in understanding
how yields are related to expected
returns. In simple terms, higher yield
mechanically means lower exposure to the
underlying asset by being short a higher
delta option and correspondingly it
means lower expected returns. When you
sell the call option, you receive an
option premium that feels like income
and is packaged up and distributed by
covered call funds as a cash
distribution. But the fund now has this
liability, the potential need to sell
the underlying shares below their market
value if the price rises above the
strike price. This liability exists
until the position is sold or the option
expires. Remember, the expected return
of the short call is increasingly
negative with an increasing derivative
yield. Here's why this matters. Over the
full life cycle of this type of trade,
the outcome is generally worse than
simply having held the underlying
equity. Part of the reason is a lower
equity beta, meaning less exposure to
the equity risk premium. To be clear,
this is something that you could do by
simply reducing your exposure to the
stock directly and holding some cash.
I'll come back to that with an example
later. The problem is that the reduction
in exposure to the equity risk premium
is also asymmetric. You keep most of the
downside while capping your upside at
the strike price. This means that
through any periods of market
volatility, which are of course common
in equities, in stocks, you eat most of
the downside, but you do not participate
in a large portion of the upside.
Systematically missing out on stock
market recoveries, which are common
after major downturns, can be very
expensive. Before I continue, I do need
to mention a potential saving grace for
covered calls. The volatility risk
premium. Equity options tend to be
priced with an implied volatility higher
than realized volatility. This creates
the opportunity for option sellers to
earn an expected risk premium for
enduring the risk of an extreme event
where realized volatility exceeds
implied volatility. While it makes back
tested cover call strategies look really
good in recent history since about 2011,
the volatility risk premium has not been
anywhere near sufficient to offset the
reduction in equity exposure from
selling the options resulting in poor
performance for these strategies. This
kind of thing can happen when a trade
becomes too crowded by, say, the
proliferation of retail funds chasing
the strategy. I want to make sure it's
really clear that the point about
asymmetry is particularly important for
long-term equity investors who have
historically benefited from a little bit
of mean reversion in stocks, making
stocks a little bit less risky at long
horizons than they would be if returns
were completely random. In simple terms,
after stocks have performed really
poorly, they tend to perform a bit
better than average. This is in contrast
to bonds which do not tend to have the
same rebound effect after poor
performance. In fact, bonds often
continue having poor performance after
having poor performance. Based on this,
some research has suggested that the
higher expected returns and mean
reverting tendencies of stocks make them
less risky than bonds for long-term
investors, including long-term investors
who need to live off of their
investments. But here's the problem.
Selling calls on your equity positions
both lowers the expected returns and
eliminates the mean-reverting tendency
of stocks by capping the upside return
while only slightly improving the
downside by the amount of the option
premium. Again, getting most of the
downside with a limit on upside is not
good. I would argue that it makes
covered calls very risky for long-term
investors who are concerned with funding
their inflationadjusted spending. This
might be hard to believe given the large
distribution yields of these strategies.
But it's important to remember that
these distributions are not income in
the way that say bond interest is and
presenting them this way is
irresponsible. The option premiums come
with an associated liability that lowers
expected returns and transforms the
shape of the distribution of returns
into something much less favorable for
long-term investors. One of the biggest
problems I see for these funds is that
their distribution yields are often much
higher than their total expected
returns. Yet, they're occasionally
discussed in income investing and fire
communities as if their distributions
are perpetually sustainable. It even
gives some people the idea that they
should borrow money at say 5% to invest
in cover called funds with a 14%
distribution yield. The combination of
high distribution yields, lower expected
returns, an uncapped downside, and a
capped upside means that someone who's
spending the distributions could deplete
their capital fairly quickly. This is
another reason why calling these
distributions passive income is
financial If you need a
psychological trick to help you spend
down your capital, covered calls might
be the answer, but their distribution
yields are not a sustainable source of
long-term income. I'll say it one more
time. Covered calls are not good for
long-term investors. Stocks have
positive expected returns and
mean-reverting tendencies. Covered calls
reduce exposure to the underlying stocks
and chop off the right tail of the
distribution of returns, capping the
ability of the underlying to recover
from downturns. This effect compounds
over time, driving an increasingly large
wedge between the performance of the
covered call strategies and their
underlying equities. This is true in any
market conditions. I often hear that
covered calls are great in a sideways
market, but equity markets don't go
sideways. They are volatile even over
periods where they have flat returns.
Every time your covered call strategy
eats downside and is denied upside, you
are losing. Okay, that's all fine in
theory. Let's look at some live funds.
There are quite a few covered call ETFs
with reasonably long histories to
examine. These can be compared to ETFs
investing in the underlying equities
without selling calls to see all of the
points I've made so far happening in
live products. I looked for covered call
ETFs with minimum 10-year histories.
Beimo has a few that launched in 2011.
The Beimo covered call utilities ETF
launched October 20th, 2011. It
currently has a distribution yield of
7.37%
compared to 3.43% for an ETF of the
underlying equities. In periods where
the underlying equities do not perform
well, the covered call fund has been
able to outperform, but these periods
have tended to be brief and in the long
run are far more than outweighed by the
capped upside. Over the full history
since inception, the covered call fund
has trailed the underlying by an
annualized 2.6 percentage points. and it
has trailed the underlying in more than
70% of three-year rolling periods with a
one-mon step. Increasing the rolling
window to four years results in the
covered call fund trailing nearly 85% of
the time. The underperformance is
particularly pronounced when the
underlying equities drop dramatically
and then recover, which is a pretty
typical characteristic of equity
returns. As I mentioned earlier, I also
mentioned earlier that reducing equity
beta by holding cash can get you to a
similar place as a covered call, at
least from the perspective of beta. I
ran a portfolio of 60% Beimo equal
weight utilities and 40% cash well high
interest savings account from October
2013 through August 25th 2025. You can
see they track pretty closely most of
the time except that the covered call
fund gives up extreme upside events and
eats the whole meal on the downside. I
won't keep repeating that equity plus
cash comparison, but Jeff Pac, managing
director for Morning Star Research
Services, recently showed in a sample of
22 single stock covered call ETFs that a
combination of cash and the underlying
stock outperformed most of the funds had
lower volatility than all of the funds
and had a higher sharp ratio than most
of the funds. Another Beimo fund with a
reasonably long history is the Beimo
Covered Call Can Canadian Banks fund. It
launched January 28th, 2011. It has a
current distribution yield of 6.13%
compared to 3.61% for an ETF of the
underlying equities. It has
underperformed by an annualized 2.71
percentage points since inception and it
has only outperformed in less than 1% of
rolling 3-year periods since inception.
The Global X S&P TSX 60 covered call ETF
launched on March 16th, 2011. It
currently has a distribution yield of
7.67%.
It has trailed the EyesShares S&P TSX 60
ETF by 3.65 percentage points since
inception and it has trailed in 92% of
three-year rolling periods since
inception. I can go on, but you get the
idea. Covered calls are not good for
long-term investors who expect positive
returns from the underlying assets. The
ones I have mentioned so far are pretty
tame with distribution yields in the 6
to 7% range. I think where these
products really go off the rails is when
they push for even higher yields.
Remember from earlier, if you want
higher income on your covered call
strategy, you can sell options with
lower strike prices, resulting in higher
income, and higher short delta. In other
words, targeting a higher income
exacerbates all of the issues I've
mentioned with covered calls. Lower
strike prices result in higher
distribution yields, less exposure to
the underlying equity, and a tighter cap
on upside performance. Hamilton ETF's
yield maximizer ETF series targets
yields well over 10% by selling at the
money call options. Take their US equity
yield maximizer ETF as an example. It
targets a distribution yield of 12% and
has underperformed an S&P 500 ETF by an
annualized 4.48 percentage points over
its admittedly short history. I also
want to mention JAPI. This is JP
Morgan's equity premium income ETF. It
gained a cult-like following around 2022
when it outperformed the S&P 500 by
nearly 15 percentage points. That
combined with its prominently marketed
high distribution yield has made it
extremely popular with retail investors
in general and income focused investors
in particular. It even has its own
subreddit. The problem is that like
other covered call strategies, it has
underperformed an S&P 500 ETF. In this
case, by 5.92 percentage points since
inception in May 2020. This one's not a
perfect comparison to the underlying
equity since JAPI's underlying equity
portfolio is actively managed. I don't
know if blaming the underperformance on
active management or uncovered calls is
worse, but in either case, we know these
things generally don't play out well for
investors in the long run. The most
recent and ridiculous development I've
seen in the covered call space is single
stock covered call ETFs. These are
exactly what they sound like, covered
calls on single stocks in an ETF rapper.
Some of their distribution yields are
astronomical, but as you might expect by
now, so is their underperformance. TSLY
writes covered calls on Tesla shares.
Its distribution rate at the time of
writing is 48.59%.
But since inception in November 22, it
has underperformed Tesla by more than 20
percentage points annualized. These
numbers are ridiculous, but they
certainly do highlight the previously
mentioned relationship between high
derivative income yields and low
expected returns. The last point worth
mentioning is that covered call funds
will tend to have higher fees and
transaction costs than funds holding
their underlying equities. For the
sample of funds that I mentioned in this
video, excluding the single stock fund,
the average management expense ratio is
0.63%. 63% and the average trading
expense ratio is 0.16%.
While funds holding the same underlying
equities have an average management
expense ratio of 0.25% and an average
trading expense ratio of 0%. You are
paying a significant premium to access
all of the downsides of covered calls.
Those high income distributions have to
be really really psychologically
important to you for all of this to make
sense. For completeness, I do want to
say that some investment managers may
successfully use covered calls to access
the volatility risk premium, but this is
a fairly esoteric risk premium that is
probably not required for the typical
household saving for or living in
retirement. Even if there is a
volatility risk premium worth pursuing,
covered call funds are typically
marketed to retail investors based on
their distribution yields, not their
exposure to the volatility risk premium.
In my opinion, selling these products on
their yield, which in the case of
covered calls is inversely related to
their expected returns shows
indifference to the truth. It is bullit,
especially when it's held up next to
things like treasury bill yields. Taken
together, covered calls don't have
anything special to offer. They get you
to a place similar to holding a bunch of
cash, except that your upside is limited
and your downside is unlimited. They're
more likely to be detrimental to most
investors expected outcomes than to
improve them. Their high yields come at
the expense of lower expected returns
and historically lower realized returns.
The volatility risk premium, which could
theoretically help covered calls recoup
their lower expected returns, has not
been anywhere near sufficient to offset
the reduction in expected returns since
around 2011. All of these downsides show
up very clearly in the terrible
long-term performance of live covered
call strategies when measured properly
by their total returns. Thanks for
watching. I'm Ben Felix, chief
investment officer at PWL Capital. If
you enjoyed this video, please share it
with someone who thinks the 14%
distribution yield undercovered call
fund is an expected return.